I’m often asked
what my opinion
about a diet
or disease is.
Who cares what my or
anyone else’s opinion is.
All we should care about
is what the science says.
What does the best available
balance of evidence
Published in the peer-
reviewed medical literature
have to say right now?
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
It’s time for the Nutrition
Facts Grab Bag,
where we look at
the latest science
on a whole variety
of topics.
And we start today with
a story on the micromort.
And no, that’s not a nickname
for your short uncle.
Think of it as a unit of comparing
and communicating risk to patients.
Hundreds of millions of operations
are performed every year,
and the risk of death is
typically around a half a percent,
to which patients might say things like,
“I could die just as
easily crossing the road,”
making it clear they
really don’t understand
the difference in magnitude of risk.
One way to communicate
risk is by analogy.
For example, just going
under anesthetic carries about
a 1 in 100,000 chance you won’t
wake up. How much is that?
Well, that’s about the same
risk as an expert sky dive.
Okay, but that still may be kind
of hard to wrap your head around.
It's hard to think in
terms of small numbers.
Imagine discussing a
0.0017 mile x 0.00227 mile rug.
How big even is that?
We need more digestible units.
Enter the micromort
as a unit of comparing
and communicating risk to patients.
A micromort is a unit equivalent to
one in a million chance of dying.
One in a million is like
the chances of ﬂipping a coin
and getting 20 heads or tails in a row,
or a little less than the
chances of getting a royal flush.
But the real utility is to help
compare different risks to one another,
using the same metric.
For example, driving a
hundred miles entails about
a one in a million chance of
death, so that’s one micromort.
Scuba diving is like
five micromorts per dive;
so, each dive is as risky
as driving 500 miles.
So, now we have a way to
directly compare the risk
of surgical procedures
and common activities.
Giving birth is as risky as driving
from NY to LA and then back again,
but getting a cesarean is
more than twice as risky.
Even something like a simple hernia
repair carries the same risk
of dying as like sky diving 200 times.
Now obviously, sometimes
you have no choice,
but death from varicose vein
surgery or circumcision
could probably be avoided.
I was surprised to learn
that regular horseback riding
is like four times deadlier
than rock climbing,
but getting chemo and radiation
for head and neck cancer
is riskier than rock-
climbing for 500 years,
driving 5 million miles, or
jumping 5,000 sky dives, etc.
One leading cause of death
I really didn’t talk about
in How Not to Die is
accidental death.
We have approximately a one
in a million chance of dying
just by accident every day of our lives,
and about half of that risk
is dying in a car crash,
based on U.S. averages.
Then, there are all sorts of other ways.
I am surprised to learn Americans
have about a 1 in 200,000 chance
every year of dying from a
foreign body entering an orifice
other than the mouth.
Other things we may want to avoid
include climbing Mount Everest,
about 30 times riskier than
coal mining or base jumping.
Trains and planes are actually
equivalent over the same distance,
but riding a motorcycle is about 50 times
deadlier than riding in a car,
though cycling to a
destination is riskier too,
about 10 times as deadly
as driving in the near term.
Here’s a good example of how one
can use micromort comparisons
to help put things in perspective.
Certain types of breast implants
can cause a rare type of cancer,
a type of breast implant-
associated lymphoma.
You can imagine how scary this is
for the millions of women
who have implants,
but check out the risk compared to
the risk of other common activities.
Your risk of dying from
this kind of cancer is less
than a single day of skiing.
Now, it’s probably better to
die quick on the slopes
than all the slow suffering of cancer,
and risk of bankrupting your family,
but at least it can put the
risk of the implant-cancer
killing you in context.
In our next story we ask,
do nut eaters live longer
simply because they swap
in protein from plants
in place of animal protein?
The American Journal of Clinical
Nutrition is the highest ranked
peer-reviewed scientific
journal in nutrition.
That should tell you a lot about
the field, since it’s published
by the American Society of Nutrition,
whose sustaining partners
include The Sugar Association, candy
bar and soda companies,
the corn syrup people, and the meat,
dairy, and egg industries.
And this is the highest
ranked nutrition journal.
The fact that the National Cattlemen’s
Beef Association is a
sustaining partner may help explain
their publication of this article.
Imagine you’re in the pocket
of Big Beef and Big Pig.
How could you possibly pull off a
study showing that eating red meat
does not negatively inﬂuence
cardiovascular disease risk factors?
A meta-analysis of randomized
controlled trials showing that
eating more versus less red
meat does not inﬂuence
cholesterol or blood pressure.
Dr.’s Barnard and Willett pointed
out the fatal flaw in their editorial
“The Misuse of Meta-analysis
in Nutrition Research,”
by asking the question “Compared to What?”
Of the 39 trials that they
had chosen on LDL cholesterol,
nearly 90 percent of them were
just swapping one meat for another,
comparing red meat to white meat.
They were using chicken control
diets or fish control diets.
And we know that when it
comes to cholesterol,
the impact of beef consumption
is just as bad as fish or poultry,
and so that’s how they pulled it off.
They just swapped meats.
That’s like publishing a study saying
total Twinkie intake does not
negatively inﬂuence risk factors by
switching Twinkies with Ding Dongs.
Those randomized to zero
Twinkies didn’t do any better.
Yeah, because now they
were eating Ding Dongs.
It’s a classic drug industry trick:
testing your drug against
something known to be terrible.
Whereas if you swap out meat for
plant-based meats—plant-based sausages,
plant-based chicken
patties, and veggie dogs—
you end up with significantly
lower cholesterol.
Well duh, you say, there’s less
saturated fat in plant-based meats.
But even independent of saturated
fat content, you end up with
higher LDL cholesterol with
red meat or white meat—
any kind of meat—compared to
non-meat protein sources.
The researchers conclude that
this is keeping with recommendations
promoting diets with a high
proportion of plant-based food but,
based on cholesterol effects, white
meat like chicken and turkey
is just as bad as red.
And fish may be even worse, though
what they often did is try to
standardize the saturated fat
content by adding like butter.
But at the same saturated fat
content, fish appears to be worse
than beef, and chicken is
just as bad as beef.
Yet plant protein sources like
legumes, soy, and nuts–
so beans, split peas, chickpeas, lentils,
soybeans, and nuts—did better.
Switch out a single serving of even
lean beef with the same amount
of calories of nuts or soybeans, and
you can lower LDL bad cholesterol,
a key risk factor for the
#1 killer of men and women
in the United States and
around much of the world.
But wait, is that why a single
serving of nuts a day is associated
with 22 percent reduction in
the risk of premature death?
Why millions of deaths every
year may be attributable to
inadequate nut intake?
Maybe the benefit is just because
they’re eating nuts instead of meat?
No. The drop of heart attacks
amongst more frequent nut eaters
is just as strong or even
stronger among vegetarians.
The reduced mortality associated
with nut consumption
is independent of health condition.
It’s not just health nuts eating nuts.
In fact, in a comparison of
a dozen different food groups,
nuts beat out even
vegetables when it came to
a lower risk of premature death.
Finally today, we look at the secret
to the public health community’s triumph
when past attempts to regulate
the food industry had failed.
There are three broad approaches to
mediating the ruin of risky choices:
inform people (like using labeling),
nudge people (for example, by
offering financial incentives),
or directly intervene to make
the activity less harmful.
Which do you think
prevented more car fatalities:
mandating driver education,
labeling cars about crash risk,
or removing the human element
altogether by just making sure
air bags are installed?
There are public education nutrition
campaigns from "sugar pack" ads
on public transit, informing consumers
how much sugar is in soft drinks,
to "Hot Dogs Cause Butt Cancer"
billboards, educating about the link
between processed meat
and colorectal cancer.
But is there a way to make products
nutritionally safer in the first place?
The ban on trans fats
offers a useful lesson.
In 1993, the Harvard Nurses Study
found that high intake of trans fat
may increase the risk
of heart disease by 50%.
That's where the trans fat
story started in Denmark,
and it ended a decade later
with a ban on added
trans fats there in 2003.
It took another 10 years, though,
before the U.S. even started
considering a ban. All the while,
trans fats were killing an estimated
tens of thousands
of Americans every year,
resulting in as many years
of healthy life lost as conditions
like meningitis, cervical cancer,
and multiple sclerosis.
If so many people were
suffering and dying,
why did it take so long for the U.S.
to even suggest taking action?
One can look at a fight over
New York City's trans fat ban
for a microcosm
of the national debate.
Opposition came down hard from
the food industry, complaining
about government intrusion,
likening the city to a "nanny state."
Since trans fats can be naturally
found in meat and dairy,
the livestock industry echoed
the Institute of Shortening's
"everything-in-moderation" argument.
Critics styled such proposals
as the rise of food fascism.
But it was the restaurant and food
industries that limited consumer choice
by so broadly fouling the food supply
with these dangerous fats.
If food zealots get their wish
in banning added trans fats—
another argument went—
what's next?
Vested corporate interests tend to rally
around these kinds of slippery slope
arguments to try to distract from the
very real fact that people are dying.
I mean what if the government
tries to make us eat broccoli?
This actually came up in a Supreme
Court case over Obamacare.
Chief Justice Roberts suggested
Congress could start
ordering everyone
to buy vegetables,
a fear Justice Ginsburg
dubbed the broccoli horrible.
Technically, Congress could compel the
American public to eat more plant-based,
Justice Ginsburg wrote, yet
one can't offer the hypothetical
and unreal possibility of a vegetarian
state as a credible argument.
As one legal scholar put it, "Judges
and lawyers live on the slippery slope
of analogies; they're not
supposed to ski it to the bottom."
New York City finally
won its trans fat fight,
preserving its status
as a public health leader.
For example, New York banned lead
paint 18 years before federal action
was taken, despite decades of
unequivocal evidence of its harm.
Comparing stroke and heart attack
rates before and after the rollout of
the trans fat ban in different New York
counties, researchers estimate it
successfully reduced cardiovascular
death rates by about 5%.
This then became the model for
the nationwide ban years later.
How was the public health
community able to triumph
when attempts in the past to regulate
the food industry failed?
If you would have asked me about
the odds of a national trans fat ban,
I would have said, "fat chance."
In Denmark, as a leading
Danish cardiologist put it,
"Instead of warning consumers
about trans fats and telling them
what they are, we've
simply removed them."
But we're Americans!
As they say here:
"You can put poison in the
food if you label it properly."
If people know the risks,
the argument goes,
then they should be able
to eat whatever they want.
But that's assuming they've
been given all the facts,
which isn't always the case,
given the food industry's model
of systemic dishonesty,
as one health ethics professor put it.
Given the predilection for predatory
deception and manipulation,
government intervention
was deemed necessary,
but how are you going
to get it passed?
First, there was a
labeling requirement.
Manufacturers had to start adding
trans fat content to products'
nutrition facts labeling. Ostensibly
this was to influence consumers,
but it may have had a bigger
impact on producers.
Now that they had to divulge
the truth, companies scrambled
to reformulate their products to gain
a "no trans fat" competitive edge.
Within years of the mandatory
disclosure, more than 5,000 products
were introduced touting low
or zero trans fats on their labels.
Kentucky Fried Chicken went from being
sued for having some of the highest
trans fat levels to running an ad
campaign where mom tells dad
in front of kids that KFC now
has zero grams of trans fat,
and the father yells,
"Yeah, baby! Whoooo!!"
and begins eating fried
chicken by the bucketful.
That was the secret
to passing the ban.
Once the major food industry players
had already reformulated their products
and bragged about it, once there
wasn't so much money at stake,
then there was insufficient
political will to block the ban
and added trans fats were
taken off the playing field.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.